<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jake Fleming</title>
    <description>Thoughts and work related to product design.</description>
    <link>http://jakefleming.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jakefleming.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 00:17:28 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 00:17:28 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Surround yourself</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Surround yourself with people who are better than you. I learned this lesson early in life, and I’m relearning it now. When you’re surrounded by people who excel at things you wish you were better at, you’ll inevitably get better at those things more quickly. Whether it’s out of fear of looking stupid, desire to impress peers, straight-up envy, or most likely, a combination of all those things at once, you will surely observe your skills growing at a much faster pace than if you were simply trying to improve them hiding away in solitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-slight-anectode&quot;&gt;A slight anectode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was very young, I’d spend countless hours drawing. My grandfather is a painter, and he’d give me tips. He’d share his techniques and principles with me–How to achieve different moods by playing around with color, how to evoke emotion and movement through repetition of shape, and how to use stark contrast to bring focus to a particular area of the canvas. I’d sit and watch as he would skillfully mix his collection of oil paints and do my best to help him dream up new scenes for his newest masterpiece. He’d sketch a few basic shapes on an artboard that would soon magically change into colorful horses galloping away from a fire-bright carnival carousel, or rolling waves crashing against a rocky shore–purple, blue, and black beneath a pale moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t learn about design with a capital “D” until much later in life, but I believe these fundamental principles that I was exposed to at such an early age were bricks in a path that would eventually lead to my career in design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be surrounded by people who were better than me by default on a daily basis. My family is full of singers, musicians, artists, actors, and designers. I aspired to be good at each and every one of the things that interested me. My mom was the choir director at church. Her voice was so incredibly beautiful. I’d wake up to her rehearsing songs while whipping up oatmeal cookies or tidying up junk that either my sister, brother, or I had left out the night before. Waking up to her song was something I always took for granted. Looking back, I realize it was one of the things that set me on the path I’m trekking down today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up watching cartoons and playing pretty much any game I could get my hands on is what fueled an already growing interest in illustration. I just had to recreate every character and every thing I was watching or playing at the time. I wasn’t very good at it, yet I powered through compulsively, and a strange but obvious result came of all of this mimicry. I became pretty amazing at illustrating things. Not only could I mimic just about anything, I was also developing my own taste and deviating from pure plagiarism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started creating my own characters and my own stories. My older brother was also really great at illustration–much better than I was. It was extremely annoying. We’d spend hours creating characters with intricate backstories and fantastical nemeses. His were always better. I didn’t understand it. I’d get better and better each day, but he’d always be a step or two ahead of me. The fact was, my brother had just been doing it longer, he had more experience, and was frankly genuinely better than me when it came to illustration. He probably still is, and I do these things for money. Without somebody blazing the trail, I wonder if I would have kept up with it so rigorously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently fallen into a similar situation at my current job, coleading the Product Design track at Tradecraft with Zac Halbert and Michael Burkett (Though Michael recently left to cofound something that I’m sure will be amazing). I’m surrounded by so many talented people every single day I walk through those doors. It’s incredible–and it’s not just the other instructors at Tradecraft. The students are all coming in with varying degrees of expertise in all sorts of areas. Some have a rich history in 3D animation. Some were architects in a past life. Some were developers, attorneys, or mechanical engineers–some even have hopes to play a part in shaping the new(ish) frontier of VR. There are so many things I desperately need to get better at, and luckily I’m able to spend my days around people who are better at those things. I’m surprised each week how much information I’m able to absorb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job prior to Tradecraft was at a small consultancy in Chicago called Appiphony where I was helping to design enterprise apps on top of Salesforce. We were doing some pretty interesting work there, specifically in the healthtech industry. It was the first time in my design career where I had the opportunity to make a measurable difference in people’s lives. I had the pleasure of working with some extremely talented people. There was a very strong culture of learning that drew me in while interviewing with the team. Another situation surrounded by people who were better than me at things I was interested in getting better at. Writing HTML and CSS was something I had done in the past as well as writing some pretty shoddy JQuery, but I never thought that I’d become the person who owned every line of CSS and most of the HTML that was going to production. By the end of my time at Appiphony, the dev team solely relied on me to write all CSS and came to me when there were bugs. It was an amazing feeling, and I will always attribute my vast knowledge of obscure css bugs to my time there in Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no better way to learn a thing than to actually do that thing, and there’s no better way to get better and better at that thing than to surround yourself with at least three kinds of people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-you&quot;&gt;Future you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “future you” is a person that either has a particular skill or a particular job you aspire to have in the near or distant future. These “future yous” act as a beacon steering you away from a rocky shore or throwing you a life raft when you’re in too deep. You should meet with these types of people at least once a month. If you have a chance to be around a “future you” more than once a month without getting on their nerves, do it. Learn their stories, aspirations, and what they’re working on. Best case scenario, you’re able to be around future yous on a daily basis. Concentrate on providing as much value to them as they are providing to you. Afterall, don’t you want “future you” to feel happy and successful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;present-you&quot;&gt;Present you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “present you” is a person who is at the same level as you are in terms of his or her skillset or career. They’re in the same boat as you are, rowing along and hoping to hear someone shout, “Land ho!” These people might be coworkers, classmates, friends, enemies, acquaintances you met at a meetup. The thing they should all have in common is that they’re working toward the same or very similar set of goals. The reason I’m including enemies in that list is because a little, heck, even a lot of competition can do wonders for motivation. Just don’t make enemies out of friends. Designers need to stick together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;past-you&quot;&gt;Past you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A “past you” is somebody who’s aspiring to get to your level in terms of skillset or career. In this scenario, you are the future you to your past you. You are the beacon. You are the mentor. You are the sagely instructor. You should take every possible chance to help out fellow designers who are following in your footsteps. Tell them the things you wish you knew when you were in their shoes. You might think to yourself, “But I don’t want to give away my secrets. I got to where I am without knowing these things. Why should they get that benefit when I had to figure it out myself?” Well, that’s a mighty fine sob story and everything, but being a designer isn’t about keeping secrets. It’s about solving real problems for real people. Share your successes and failures and don’t be a dick.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 15:42:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jakefleming.net/surround-yourself</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jakefleming.net/surround-yourself</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
